Well, all right. I reckon it's time we
talked about the experience of black
Americans in the period from 1800 to
1848. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milt, let's get to it. Okay.
So, let's begin by setting the stage and
thinking about continuity and change
during this period. Now, here's where I
tell you that most of the founders, even
those who owned enslaved people like
Thomas Jefferson and George Washington,
believe that slavery was an institution
unbecoming of a free nation. I mean,
everyone was running around crying
liberty. And it felt just a little uh
illfitting that such a large population
of the United States was enslaved. But
even so, they made almost no efforts to
legally abolish the institution since
they held a firm conviction that with
the banning of the international slave
trade in 1808 and the eventual
exhaustion of southern soil by cotton
cultivation, slavery would essentially
abolish itself. A so naive. So in terms
of continuity, slavery remained a
significant institution present in early
19th century America. Oh, and by the
way, if you want note guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
check the link in the description. But
change was also a foot, my dear people.
In the north, a growing abolitionist
movement led to the banning of slavery
in all northern states. Some of which
mandated immediate abolition, while
others allowed for gradual emancipation.
Now, I am in no way poo pooing such an
effort. No, abolition in any form gets
all the thumbs up for me. But I need to
mention that abolishing slavery in the
north wasn't the heaviest lift since
their enslaved population was very small
and they in no way relied on slavery for
economic flourish. It's kind of like if
a person has never gotten drunk in their
lives because they just don't like the
taste of alcohol, then their sobriety is
not really a virtue. was just a
preference that cost them very little.
But at least some efforts to abolish
slavery in the North were surely a moral
crusade, especially the abolitionist
Christian denominations that embraced
the impulse for social reform as a
result of the Second Great Awakening.
And then to further complicate the
issue, while the North was getting
itself all free of slavery and wagging
its moralistic finger at the backward
southern slave holders, they apparently
felt just fine importing metric
buttloads of southern cotton into their
factories that had been processed by the
enslaved. But in the South, we see a
very different reality. You see, while
the northern economy was almost entirely
centered on industrial manufacturing,
the southern economy was entirely
centered on agriculture and specifically
the growth and export of cotton. Now,
the cultivation of cotton required
massive tracks of land and a whole lot
of human labor to plant and harvest. And
so, at the very same time that northern
states were abolishing slavery, southern
states were becoming even more
entrenched in the institution since
their very livelihood depended on its
perpetuation. And in order to do this,
slaveholders increasingly relied on and
perpetuated several justifications for
slavery in order to make the brutal
institution more palatable. And chief
among these arguments was to frame
slavery as a positive good rather than a
necessary evil and to argue that
enslaved labor was superior to wage
slavery in the North. We'll talk all
about that in the next video. So for
now, I'll leave it there. Okay. Now,
we'll come back to slavery in a minute,
but first let me tell you about the
population of free blacks during this
period. Now, it might surprise you to
hear that the free black populations in
both the north and the south were
roughly equal in number, but their
experiences were different. So, in the
north, many free blacks lived in cities
where they were able to own land and
live together in families. However, even
though the north was boiling with
anti-slavery movements, that did not
necessarily translate into equal rights
for free blacks. So, if in your mind you
think of northern states during this
period as a shining beacon of liberty
and equality for black people, well,
you're going to need to go ahead and
shut that all the way down. In fact, for
a substantial portion of abolitionists,
their main concern was not encouraging
equality between white and black
Americans, but rather their main concern
was economics. What I mean is many
abolitionists believe that the
perpetuation of enslaved labor
challenged the viability of free wage
labor, which was predominant in the
north. In fact, one of the most
prominent features of the abolitionist
movement was the formation of the
American colonization society. And
basically this organization argued that
since black and white people were in
fact not equal and could never coexist,
let's establish a colony in Africa,
namely Liberia, and just send all the
black people there. And you know, that
logic kind of resembled a kid capturing
a cricket and putting it in a jar with
some leaves and a stick. And that kid
pats himself on the back and says, "Oh,
little Randy is just going to love his
natural environment and thrive for the
rest of his days." No, for the most
part, the only people who were excited
about sending black people back to
Africa to a place where almost none of
them were actually from were white
people. So all that to say, yes, free
blacks in the north enjoyed more freedom
than their counterparts in the south,
but they were in no way enjoying the
fullness of their civil rights. Even so,
many free blacks came together to create
their own social institutions, like for
example, the predominantly black African
Methodist Episcopal Church. Anyway, in
the south, most of the free black
population also lived in cities, though
they had to deal with the constant fears
of being kidnapped and forced into
slavery. Additionally, state laws banned
them from voting and restricted the
kinds of occupations available to them.
Okay. And now, let's consider how black
Americans resisted the dehumanizing
effects of slavery. And I'll mention
three distinct categories. First,
enslaved blacks engaged in covert
resistance, which means it was kind of
undercover. For example, enslaved
Americans took pains to maintain their
own culture. In some cases, though their
white owners gave them Christian names,
they used names of West African descent
out of the hearing of their masters. In
other cases, they kept their traditions
alive through traditional African music,
played on African instruments, and told
each other traditional folk tales from
their homeland. Or another example,
enslaved people resisted bondage by
breaking tools and slowing down their
work. It meant at the very least that
the planter who enslaved them would not
enjoy as much profit as he would if the
work was at full speed. And then the
second category here is overt
resistance. And in this case, we're
talking about rebellion that was out in
the open for all to see. And I'll give
you two notable examples. First, let's
talk about Nat Turner's rebellion in
1831. Now, perhaps the deepest fear
among white enslavers was the persistent
threat of slave rebellion. I mean, the
fact that the Haitian Revolution was
successful in killing and driving out
the island's white slave masters and the
memory of the Stoneo Rebellion only
stoked this abiding fear. And then in
1831, a new slave rebellion erupted in
Virginia that proved that they were
right to be afraid. So Nat Turner was an
enslaved man who, in the opinion of his
enslavers, had been happy and content
with his lot in life. But Turner
developed the idea that he was a
religious prophet whom God had charged
with a mission to emancipate the
enslaved through violence. And so in
1831, Turner gathered his followers by
night and killed the white family who
claimed ownership over him and then
proceeded to kill more than 50 white
men, women, and children in the
surrounding area. Now, the rebellion was
quickly put down by the Virginia
militia. But this event struck deep fear
within the southern white planters. As a
result, states across the south imposed
much harsher slave codes meant to
restrict and control its enslaved
populations. But at the same time,
measures were also taken to regulate
some of the brutal treatment of the
enslaved so that they wouldn't feel the
need to rebel so dang much. That wy
planter elite just couldn't be too
careful about keeping the balance
between abject dehumanization of the
enslaved and keeping them happy enough
to be content. And spoiler alert, that
is a balance that cannot be kept on
account of the enslaved people didn't
seem to be content with any amount of
dehumanization. Okay. And then the
second example of overt resistance was
the Amastad case in 1841 which further
stoked southern fears of enslaved
rebellion. So long story short in 1839
enslaved men aboard a Spanish ship
killed the captain and took control of
the vessel. And then the US Navy
intercepted the ship and imprisoned the
rebels but due to international treaties
outlawing slavery and abolitionist
pressure. The case of these enslaved
mutineers came before the US federal
courts. Now John Quincy Adams enlisted
himself to represent the Africans and
argued for their freedom. And when the
case came before the Supreme Court, the
decision indeed freed these men. And
northern abolitionists consider this
decision a win. But Southerners were
outraged that the court would overstep
its authority by freeing enslaved
people. And so at the end of the day,
both Nat Turner's rebellion and the
Amastad case only deepened the tension
and animosity between the North and the
South. Okay. And then the last category
of resistance includes various political
efforts toward abolition. So in 1848, a
new effort to organize a political
movement against slavery emerged with
the Free Soil Convention. Frederick
Douglas, who famously broke with William
Lloyd Garrison over the efficacy of
political action against slavery, joined
the movement, believing that a new
political party could make significant
changes to slavery in America. And
ultimately, these efforts led to the
creation of a new political party known
as the Free Soil Party. And in line with
what I mentioned earlier, this party
didn't really focus on the moral
depravity of slavery. But rather, they
focused on more practical matters like
guarding Western territories against the
spread of slavery so that white workers
could continue to find opportunities on
the frontier. But even so, Douglas was a
practical man and could see that if a
candidate from the Free Soil Party won,
it would mean that the sun was setting
on American slavery. Okay, click here to
watch my other videos from unit 4 and
click here to grab my video note guides
which are going to help you get all the
contents of this course firmly crammed
into your brain fold. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. I'm lur.